Guide to the Lincoln Collection, Barton Codex Manuscripts 1829-1940
University of Chicago Library
Lincoln Collection. Barton Codex Manuscripts
1829-1940
12.5 linear feet (19 boxes, 1 volume)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Bound materials collected and compiled by William E. Barton, a pastor in Oak Park, Illinois, who published and lectured on Abraham Lincoln. The collection includes books, booklets, scrapbooks, pamphlets, published addresses, and periodicals. Of particular interest is the volume titled Lincoln and His Cabinet. These codex manuscripts form part of the William E. Barton Collection of Lincolniana.
Information on Use
Access
This collection is open for research.
Digital Images
Original documents, texts, and images represented by digital images linked to this finding aid are subject to U. S. copyright law. It is the user's sole responsibility to secure any necessary copyright permission to reproduce or publish documents, texts, and images from any holders of rights in the original materials.
The University of Chicago Library, in its capacity as owner of the physical property represented by the digital images linked to this finding aid, encourages the use of these materials for educational and scholarly purposes. Any reproduction or publication from these digital images requires that the following credit line be included: Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center, University of Chicago Library.
Commercial publication projects require the permission of the University of Chicago Library and may be subject to a use fee. To order publication-quality reproductions, or for permission to copy or use any part of the digital images attached to this finding aid for any commercial purposes, please contact the Special Collections Research Center.
The images presented here may include materials reflecting the attitudes, language, and stereotypes of an earlier time period. These materials are presented as historical resources in support of study and research. Inclusion of such materials does not constitute an endorsement of their content by the University of Chicago.
The University of Chicago Library appreciates hearing from anyone who may have information about any of the images in this collection.
Biographical Note
The Rev. William Eleazar Barton, born on June 28, 1861 (d. December 30, 1930) was one of the early twentieth century's most prominent writers and lecturers on the life of Abraham Lincoln. Born in Sublette, Illinois, in the same year Lincoln assumed the presidency, Barton grew up in an environment heavily influenced by reverence for Lincoln. He began undergraduate studies at Berea College in 1881 and graduated in 1885. However, during his senior year Barton decided to join the ministry and was ordained on June 6, 1885. On July 23, 1885 Barton married Esther Treat Bushnell. Together they would have 5 children. Barton returned to school and earned his divinity degree from the Oberlin Theological Seminary in 1890. He served parishes in Tennessee, Ohio, and Massachusetts before becoming the pastor of the First Congregational Church of Oak Park, Illinois, a position he held until his retirement in 1924. In 1928, Barton accepted an appointment as lecturer at Vanderbilt University in Nashville, Tennessee, where he also organized and served as pastor of the Collegeside Congregational Church.
Barton's work as a writer produced a number of denominational manuals and a series of books presenting the wisdom and parables of a character he named Safed the Sage. For the last ten years of his life, however, Barton was best known to the public as a prolific author and lecturer on Abraham Lincoln. His publications about Lincoln included The Soul of Abraham Lincoln (1920), The Paternity of Abraham Lincoln (1920), The Life of Abraham Lincoln (1925), The Great and Good Man (1927), The Women Lincoln Loved (1927), and The Lincoln of the Biographers (1930).
In the course of compiling material for his writings and talks, Barton visited Lincoln sites in Kentucky, Indiana, and Illinois; interviewed surviving Lincoln relatives and acquaintances; and traveled as far as California and England to collect information and conduct genealogical research on the ancestry of the Lincoln family. While acquiring a large collection of books, periodicals, pamphlets, manuscripts, and ephemera related to Lincoln and the Civil War era, Barton also purchased privately or at auction historical materials amassed by other Lincoln collectors such as John E. Burton and Osborn H. Oldroyd.
Scope Note
The Barton Codex Manuscripts is made up of bound materials compiled by William E. Barton, a pastor in Oak Park, Illinois, who published and lectured on Abraham Lincoln extensively. Barton also maintained connections with fellow Lincoln experts and carried out multiple research projects that delved into the many facets of Lincoln's life, times, and family history. This collection divided into six series: ministry; books; theater; booklets, pamphlets and periodicals; published addresses, lectures and research papers; and lastly, scrapbooks. Of particular interest is the volume titled Lincoln and His Cabinet. These codex manuscripts form part of the William E. Barton Collection of Lincolniana.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Barton, William Eleazar, 1861-1930; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Collectors and collecting -- United States; American Civil War, 1861-1865; Church History
INVENTORY
- Series I: Barton Ministry
  This series contains materials related to Barton's career in the Ministry, including books, sermons and sermon notes, clippings and articles.
  - First Presbyterian Church Board of Trustees Minutes, Springfield, Illinois, 1829-1866 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Press notices of sermons and addresses by William E. Barton, news-clippings and notes tipped in, 1894-1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Notes and correspondence, from ledger of church finances, 1903-1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Actual ledger of church finances 1903-1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Addresses and articles on ministry, containing correspondence, reprints, and clippings, 1911-1928 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Order for Evening Worship, Boston: F. H. Gilson Company, 1892. Notes and news-clippings tipped in, 1911-1928 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Addresses and articles on education, containing interleaved notes, articles, and reprints, 1913-1926 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Papers removed from Addresses and articles on education, 1913-1926 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Church programs and bulletins from Lent, Holy Week, and Easter, 1914-1923 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Sermon Outline", sermon notes and outlines (of Barton's), 1915 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Clippings removed from "Sermon Outline", 1915 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bound clippings from Barton's column "The Making of the New Testament," 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Notes and news-clippings in volume titled "Annual Handbook, Central Congregational Church," 1915 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Calendar, contains interleaved notes and news-clippings, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ministry programs and bulletins, 1897-1922, Program from the Boston Congregational Club Forefathers Festival (at which Barton spoke), December 21, 1897 Barton, William E. "Our Fight for the Heritage of Humanity," sermon published by the Men's Bible Class, Congregational Church, Oak Park, Illinois, 1917 Bulletin for service at First Congregational Church, Oak Park, Illinois, where Barton delivered the sermon, "The Abiding Influence of George Washington," 1920 Barton, William E. "Theodore Roosevelt," sermon, 1920 Bulletin for service at First Congregational Church, Oak Park, Illinois, where Barton delivered the sermon, "Theodore Roosevelt," 1920 Information for visitors to the Parish Church of St. Nicholas, Great Yarmouth, 1923 The Open Court: A Monthly Magazine, vol. XXXVIII (No. 9), 1922 The Open Court: A Monthly Magazine, vol. XXXVII (No. 10), 1922 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Barton, William E., Theodore G. Soares, and Sidney Strong. Su Ultima Semana: La Historia de la Pasion y Resurrection de Jesus, Chihuahua: Imprenta Palmore, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bound clippings regarding Barton's lecture series titled "The Religion of the Ancient Poets," 1923 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series II: Books
  - Abraham Lincoln and His Cabinet: A Collection of Autographs, 1851-1889 (Volume BartonCdx1)
  - Worcester, J.E. Elements of History, Ancient and Modern, includes note by Barton, 1833 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence of Robert Weidensall. prepared by the Illinois Historical Records Survey Project in 1940, correspondence dates from 1861-1865 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Hale, Edward E. Seven Spanish Cities. Boston: Roberts Brothers, 1883, with letter from Barton, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Barton, William E. Lieutenant William Barton of Morris County, New Jersey, and his Descendants. Oak Park, Ill.: Vaile Press, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mary Lincoln: A letter to Her Cousin Elizabeth Todd Grimsly, letter written on September 29, 1861, privately printed, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Barton, William E. Abraham Lincoln and His Books, Marshall Field and company, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Wilson, Clarence True. John Wilkes Booth: Thirty-Eight Years a Fugitive, includes correspondence, 1922? (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Barton, William E. Abraham Lincoln, American, etched book and letter, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Lincoln, Waldo. History of the Lincoln Family, Worcester Massachusetts Commonwealth Press, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Barton, William E. Esther T. Barton: A Biographical Sketch. Foxboro, Mass.: Pine Knoll, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Townsend, William H. Lincoln in His Wife's Home, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Grimsley, Elizabeth Todd. Six Months in the White House, 1926-1927 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Barton, William E. The Women Lincoln Loved, printer's dummy, autographed copy, Bobbs-Merrill, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Smith, T.V. Lincoln, Living Legend, The University of Chicago Press, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Baber, Adin. Nancy Hanks of "Undistinguished Families—Second Families", typed and mimeographed by C. Gerald Brann, Bloomington IN, c. 1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Index to Adin Baber, Nancy Hanks of "Undistinguished Families, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Baber, Adin. Nancy Hanks, The Destined Mother of a President, privately printed by author, Kansas, Illinois, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Blair, Montgomery. Not General Grant, manuscript presented to Hon. Gideon Welles, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Series III: Theater
  This series contains manuscripts of plays and other documents related to the theater.
  - Day, Robert. Anne Rutledge: life, love, immortality, play manuscript and correspondence, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Hermann, Lüdke. "Abraham Lincoln," a play translated from German by Robert L. Floyd, 193-? (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "A Folk Festival: Out of the Wilderness, the New Salem Years of Abraham Lincoln." Compiled by the workers of the Writers' program of the Work Projects Administration in Illinois, play presented at New Salem state park, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Neff, Elizabeth. "Abraham Lincoln as a Character in American and English drama," Master of Arts thesis, University of Oklahoma, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - McNett, Marie. Cradle of Glory: A Drama in Three Acts, play manuscript, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Booklets, Pamphlets, and Periodicals
  - Irwin, Benjamin F. Lincoln's Religious Belief, clipped from Illinois State Journal, 1874 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Herndon, W.H. A Brief Analysis of Lincoln's Character. letter to J.E. Remsburg, 1887 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Unwritten History: The Secret Movement to Supersede Abraham Lincoln in '64." The New York Sun, includes unpublished letters of Horace Greeley, Charles Sumner, Secretary Chase, 1889 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - MacDonald, Edward. Old Capp's Hill and Burial Ground with Historical Sketches, Industrial School Press, 1895 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "The Centennial Celebration of the Old Mud-Meeting House near Harrodsburg, Kentucky." August 25, 1900 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Conant, Alban Jasper. Painter of Lincoln and Other Great Men, New York Times, 1913 and A Portrait Painter's Reminiscences of Lincoln, McClure's Magazine 32:512-516, 1909-1913 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Clark, L. Pierce. Psychologic Study of Abraham Lincoln, booklet reprinted from The Psychoanalytic Review, Vol III No. I, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Martin, James M. A Defense of Lincoln's Mother: Open Letter to William E. Barton, manuscript of letter originally published in Minneapolis Journal, includes correspondence, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Barton, William E. "Lincoln, The Young Rail Splitter," Official Magazine North American young Men's Christian Association, includes correspondence, 1922 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Barton, William E. Mord Lincoln, the Woman Hater, published in the Open Court, May 1924 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Townsend, William Henry. "Lincoln the Litigant," American Bar Association Journal, includes typewritten copies of article and revision for separate publication, 1924 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Malone, Thomas J. Lincoln, "Like Washington, Was a Miller," published in The Northwestern Miller 145:6 551-569, 1926 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - City of Norwich Official Guide booklet. Includes postcards, notes, correspondence, 1927. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Carter, Mary D. "Putting First Things First," Southern Churchman, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - The Abraham Lincoln Association. Lincoln in the Year 1855: Being the Day-by-Day Activities of Abraham Lincoln During that Year, The Abraham Lincoln Association, 1929; The Abraham Lincoln Association. Lincoln in the Year 1856: Being the Day-by-Day Activities of Abraham Lincoln During that Year, The Abraham Lincoln Association, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - The Abraham Lincoln Association. Lincoln in the Year 1858: Being the Day-by-Day Activities of Abraham Lincoln During that Year, The Abraham Lincoln Association, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - The Abraham Lincoln Association. Lincoln in the Year 1859: Being the Day-by-Day Activities of Abraham Lincoln During that Year, The Abraham Lincoln Association, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - The Abraham Lincoln Association. Lincoln in the Year 1860: Being the Day-by-Day Activities of Abraham Lincoln During that Year, The Abraham Lincoln Association, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Catalogue of Herndon-Weik Lincoln Collection. Contains correspondence, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Lincoln Booklet Dedicated to Dr. Wm. Barton." Children's compositions in manuscript, 19--? (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Series V: Published Addresses, Lectures, and Research Papers
  - Lincoln, Abraham. Lincoln's first address ("His Temperance Lecture", 1842 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Lincoln, Abraham. Collection of public addresses, Kansas, 1859 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Everett, Edward. "Address following battle at Gettysburg", 1863 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - John H. Surratt. "The Assassination of Lincoln with an Account of the Several Plots for his Abduction," lecture delivered December 6, 1870, printed in Washington Star December 8, 1870 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Barton, William E. "Message to a Young Man," published address delivered at the forty-third anniversary of the Boston YMCA, 1894 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Lincoln, Abraham. Reproduction of original book compiled by Lincoln consisting of newspaper clippings of Lincoln's speeches, includes explanatory note by J. McCan Davis, 1903 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Berstorff, Count J. Abraham Lincoln as the Germans Regarded Him, public address, 1913 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Ballantine, Dr. W. G. Lincoln—America's greatest product, published lecture, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Barton, William E. "Lincoln and Illinois" addresses at Chicago Union League Club, Quincy Illinois, and Illinois State Historical Society, includes correspondence between Barton and event organizers, 1921 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Barton, William E. "The Man Who Married Lincoln's Parents", address at Harrodsburg, Kentucky, includes clippings and correspondence, 1922 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Blair, Francis G. Newton Bateman, an address given in dedication of the Newton Bateman school, includes manuscript, clippings, correspondence and event pamphlet, 1922 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Kaufman, M.S. "Abraham Lincoln, The Friend of God and Man", sermon delivered at the National Soldiers' home in California, 1922 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - McCamant, Wallace. Manuscript of lecture Lincoln in the Winter of 1861, includes correspondence, 1922 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Shaw, James. "A neglected episode in the life of Abraham Lincoln," address delivered before the Illinois State Historical Society at Springfield, 1922 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Barton, William E. Lincoln and Chicago, public address at Chicago historical Society, February 10, 1922, includes event pamphlet and related writings, 1922-1924 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Barton, William E. "Abraham Lincoln, Kentucky Mountaineer", address delivered at Berea College, 1923 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "Lincoln and the Newspapers", a published address by Charles T. White, 1923 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "Dr. Barton as a Father," toast delivered by his son Robert Barton, March 12, 1924 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Graves, Walter. Abraham Lincoln and the Common Virtues, includes lecture manuscript and correspondence, 1924 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Fortune, William. Address on Lincoln before Southwestern Indiana Historical Society, includes correspondence and clippings, 1925. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Barton, William E. "The enduring Lincoln," published address delivered in Urbana, Illinois, includes clippings and correspondence, 1928 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Henderson, Manfred. "The Handwriting of Lincoln: A Study in Identification," Los Angeles, California, 1931 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Scherger, George Lawrence. "Lincoln—a man for the ages", lecture, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Lutz, Phillip. "We stand on sacred soil today" and "The fourth of July in Lincoln's time and today", public addresses, 1935 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - "The Name and Family of Lincoln," research compiled by the Media Research Bureau, Washington D.C., 1936? (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Series VI: Scrapbooks
  The majority of Barton's scrapbooks consist of published texts into which he pasted folded newspaper clippings, prints, and notes. For additional scrapbooks see Lincoln Collection. Barton Scrapbooks.
  - Lincoln Versus Douglas scrapbook. Includes clippings and handwritten notes, 1850-1860 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Set of clippings titled "Epitaph on the XXXVII Congress: Anti-Lincoln Tract," 1862 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Cartoons from Fun, London, 1862-1869 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Untitled scrapbook filled with hand-written notes, an excerpt from John Wilkes Booth's diary, prints, and photocopied manuscripts, 1865-1925 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Set of clippings titled "Recollections of Lincoln," 1866-1904 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Catalogue of relics owned by William E. Barton and Esther T. Barton, his wife, in William Barton's hand, which also contains a reprint of Barton's "Quest of an Ancestor" from The New England Magazine, 1898 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Abraham Lincoln's Religion. William H. Herndon, includes correspondence, public lecture, and clippings of article, 1911 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Set of clippings titled "The Parentage of Abraham Lincoln by D.J. Knotts" and subtitled "Articles affirming that he was the son of John C. Calhoun," 1911 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - William E. Barton, "Church Music," loose and bound articles on religious music, 1913-1929 (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Addresses and articles on the fine arts, mostly reviews (by Barton and others) of painters and paintings, from The Advance, 1914-1915 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Papers removed from Addresses and articles on the fine arts, 1913-1915 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - The Physiognomy of Lincoln, and An Old Likeness of Lincoln, by Truman H. Bartlett, includes clippings and correspondence with William E. Barton, 1917-1921 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - "Providential Presidents" by John M. Vandermeulen, includes correspondence between Vandermeulen and Barton, 1918-1923 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Abraham Lincoln: A Study of his Personality, by Thomas Power O'Connor, includes mounted clippings from the London Daily Telegraph, August 2-3, 1920 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Abraham Lincoln as I Knew Him by John H. Littlefield n.p. c. 1891, includes clippings and correspondence, correspondence 1920 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Lincoln's First Nomination. Scrapbook includes clippings of writings by Chauncey M. Depew and funeral service materials for Jessie Harvey Robinson (d. 1918), 1920 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Mather, Otis M. "Old Hodgenville," clippings from the La Rue County Herald, 1920 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Reviews of William E. Barton's the Paternity of Abraham Lincoln. Clippings pasted over "He Shall Seek Peace", 1920-1921 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Lincoln: Anne Routledge. Clippings, photographs and correspondence, 1920-1922? (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Barton, William E. "Aunt Sallie Saunders, an interview with the youngest sister of Ann Rutledge," published interview, clippings, and memorial pamphlet, 1921-1922 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - The Parents of Abraham Lincoln, includes clippings, correspondence, and typewritten manuscript, 1922 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Barton, William E. The American Pulpit on the Death of Lincoln, includes manuscript later published in The Open Court, 1923 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Collection of Lincoln letters and articles written by Nathaniel Howard from the Cleveland Plain Dealer, 1924 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - "Force or Consent as Basis of American Government" by Dr. Mary Scrugham, includes correspondence and published debate between William H. Townsend and Dr. Scrugham, 1924 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Fitz Henry, Charles. "The Human and Divine in Lincoln, with Letters," Peoria Journal transcript, correspondence, and photograph, 1926 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Rindlaub, Martin Philip. Abraham Lincoln with reminiscences of the Freeport Debate and the Chicago Convention, includes original manuscript, correspondence, and photos, Kiwanis Magazine, 1926 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Where Lincoln Attended Church by Rev. Joseph R. Sizoo, published in The National Republic, also includes The Lincoln Pew by L.W. Allen and notes by Barton, 1926 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Untitled scrapbook of newspaper clippings about Lincoln assassination, 1865 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings removed from untitled scrapbook, 1930-1941 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Barton, William E. Jesse Head, scrapbook includes typewritten and manuscript articles, correspondence, undated (Box 19)